只有一种生物为了自己的生存
Only one creature has carved a life for itself
在地球的每一个角落留下了印迹
in every habitat on Earth.
那就是我们人类
That creature is us.
四海之内  我们仍运用自己的聪明才智
All over the world, we still use our ingenuity to survive
在荒野之地生存
in the wild places,
远离城市灯火
far from the city lights,
与原始自然面对面
face to face with raw nature.
在我们星球的最顶部
At the top of our planet lies
是地球上最渺无人烟的地方之一
one of the most remote places on Earth.
北极
The Arctic.
在冬季  这片区域连续数月
In winter, the region is frozen
被冰雪覆盖并笼罩在黑暗中
and dark for months on end.
那里没有树木  没有可以果腹的植物
There are no trees and there are no plants to eat.
上帝创造人类时
We humans weren't built to withstand
并没有想到我们要抵御如此恶劣的环境
a landscape as hostile as this.
但是  仍有四百万人居住在这里
And yet, four million people live here.
他们对这里了如指掌  依靠这点
Their survival relies upon an intimate knowledge of this,
才得以在地球最恶劣的环境中生存
the most hostile habitat on Earth.
北极
千里冰封下的生活
北极迎来了新的一年
The beginning of a new Arctic year.
经过数月黑暗的冬季
After months of winter darkness,
太阳终于重新照在这片白雪皑皑的土地上
the sun finally returns to this frozen land.
对于格陵兰岛撒图特的因纽特人来说
For the Inuit of Saattut, Greenland,
太阳再次普照大地
the sun's return
标志着狩猎季的开始
marks the beginning of their hunting calendar.
既然这些居民拥有充足的白昼
Now that the residents have enough daylight,
不可胜数的捕食机会在向他们招手
a world of opportunity opens up.
他们可以去远离城镇的地方探险
They can embark on expeditions far from town,
穿越数千公里的冰封海面
travelling across the thousands of kilometres of sea ice
到达他们的捕猎区
that lead to their hunting grounds.
多谢
这会很有用的
今天  阿莫斯・扬森
Today, Amos Jensen
和他的儿子卡尔弗雷德里克
and his son Karl-Frederik
要给他们的狗喂食
have to feed their dogs.
这些狗极其重要
Their dogs are essential.
每年这个时候  狗拉雪橇
At this time of year, the dogsled
是他们唯一的代步工具
is their only means of transportation.
这些狗对我非常重要...
猎手的生存
依赖于这些健壮的雪橇狗
因为他们的捕猎旅程会花费一些时间
Because their hunting trip could take some time,
这对父子需要一些家的温暖
father and son will need a few comforts of home,
或者直接把家带走
or even home itself.
为了找到营养丰富的狗粮
To find the most nutritious dog food,
阿莫斯和卡尔弗雷德里克
Amos and Karl-Frederik
需要在冰封的海面上穿行十几公里
need to travel many kilometres across the sea ice.
他们的目标是一只真正的北极海怪
What they're after is a real-life Arctic sea monster,
格陵兰鲨鱼
a Greenland shark.
要支撑他们的重量
To support their weight,
冰层的厚度只需有五厘米
the ice only needs to be five centimetres thick,
大约两英寸
about two inches.
这里的冰层近一米厚
This ice is nearly a metre thick,
足以支撑起一架巨型喷气飞机
and it could support a jumbo jet.
阿莫斯知道
Amos knows that
格陵兰鲨鱼喜欢吃鲸鱼肉
Greenland sharks are partial to whale meat.
他也清楚鲨鱼生活在海底深处
And he also knows they live in the deepest waters.
现在
Now,
人和狗
both men and dogs
都只能等着鲨鱼上钩
have to wait for something to take the bait.
这些可怜的狗需要食物
我真希望明天能捕到什么
当气温骤降至摄氏零下35度
As temperatures plummet to -35 degrees Celsius,
对狗来说  厚厚的皮毛可帮它们保暖
the dogs' thick fur keeps them warm.
但如果没有小木屋
But without their hut,
阿莫斯和卡尔弗雷德里克会被冻死
Amos and Karl-Frederik would freeze to death.
来看看今天这些狗能不能吃上东西
It's time to check if the dogs will eat today.
我们捕到食物了
从鱼线上传来的震动来看
From the vibrations he feels on the fishing line,
他知道他们钓到东西了
he knows they've hooked something.
是个很大的家伙
把线拉上来后他们才能知道是否是条鲨鱼
But he won't know if it's a shark until they pull it up.
猎物在海底非常深的地方
It's down so deep
他们需要把鱼线
they have to stretch their fishing line
沿着冰面拉上几百米
along the ice in hundred-metre lengths.
他们把猎物向上拉了800米
They pull their catch up a staggering 800 metres,
这一惊人的数字近帝国大厦高度的两倍
nearly twice the height of the Empire State Building.
老天  太重了
让我看看...
居然这么大
如愿以偿  他们捕到了格陵兰鲨鱼
They've caught the Greenland shark they were hoping for.
我从没见过...
体型如此庞大的鲨鱼
看看这些鳍
这条鲨鱼真够大的
格陵兰鲨鱼
The Greenland shark is
是北冰洋里唯一一种土生土长的鲨鱼
the only native Arctic shark.
是海洋中体型最庞大的食肉动物之一
It's one of the largest predators in these seas.
研究人员在它的腹中
Researchers have found caribou
发现过驯鹿  甚至还有北极熊的残骸
and even polar bears in its stomach.
连鳍都没办法从洞里拿出来
这条鲨鱼恰巧
The shark has accidentally
被鱼线缠住了尾巴
wrapped the fishing line round its tail.
这种被捕的情况并不常见
It's not the normal way to land a shark,
但既然有收获就不用计较这些
but a catch is a catch.
它在洞口卡住了
我们需要把洞凿宽点
当心
那些牙齿很锋利
阿莫斯和卡尔仅靠自己无法把鲨鱼拉上岸
Amos and Karl can't lift the shark by themselves
所以得借助那些狗的帮忙
so they enlist the help of the dogs.
这条鲨鱼长四米  超过半吨重
This shark is four metres long, weighs over half a ton
是他们抓到过的最大的一条
and is the largest they've ever caught.
但仅够给那些狗提供两周的食物
But it will only feed their 20 dogs for two weeks.
对于格陵兰岛居民
For Greenlanders,
如果他们要继续狩猎捕鱼
it is essential to have well-fed dogs
拥有健壮的狗至关重要
if they're to continue hunting and fishing.
我不敢想象
没有这些狗的生活
他们对我非常重要
他们是我留给孩子们的遗产
在北极
Here in the Arctic,
人与狗之间的情感纽带举足轻重
the bond between man and dog is so important.
如果没有这些人类最好的朋友
It's unlikely we would have colonised
我们绝不可能征服这片土地
this habitat without our best friends.
日子一天天过去
As the year moves on,
人们对生存的探索仍毫不停歇
so does the quest for survival.
纵然现在是三月
Even thought it's March,
北冰洋仍沉睡在海冰之下
the Arctic Ocean is still dominated by sea ice.
四倍于美国国土面积的土地
An area four times the size of the United States
仍覆盖在冰雪之中
is frozen over.
这片冰层将欧洲与俄罗斯
The ice connects Europe to Russia,
俄罗斯和北美洲连接起来
and Russia to North America.
在加拿大的北极区域
And here in the Canadian Arctic,
对于冰层之下的事物
people have a unique insight into
人们有着独一无二的洞察力
what lies beneath the ice.
在加拿大东北部的康奇朱斯瓦克
In Kangiqsujjuaq, northeast Canada,
卢卡西・纳帕鲁克正在观察潮汐
Lukasi Nappaaluk is watching the tides.
明天  春分的时候
Tomorrow, the spring equinox
将发生一年中规模最大的潮汐
will create the most extreme tides of the year,
带来一次绝佳的捕食机会
and a spectacular opportunity for a meal.
因纽特人居住的土地上寸草不生
我们无法耕种
但我们因纽特人有自己的生存方法
这次小潮为冰层下的
The neap tide literally opens a door
海鲜园开启了一扇门
for a garden of seafood just below the ice.
你只需找到它的位置
You just need to know where to find it.
卢卡西和朋友们用雪地车代替狗拉雪橇
Lukasi and his friends prefer snowmobiles to dogsleds.
他们也无需把遮风挡雨的屋子带在身边
And they don't bother to bring along a shelter either.
为了保护自己  躲避暴风雪
Everything they need
他们所需要的所有材料
to protect themselves from the elements
就在自己脚下
is right beneath their feet.
老人们告诉我们
"一定要会建雪屋"
因为如果你离家捕猎...
但不会建雪屋
你会被冻死
即使屋外是摄氏零下45度
Even if it's -45 degrees Celsius outside,
雪屋内也能达到温暖舒适的零上16度
body warmth can heat an igloo to a balmy +16,
足足有60度的温差
a full 60 degrees warmer.
年轻的一代
已经忘记怎么建雪屋
...但我希望这种技能
...能重新流传下去
坐在温暖的雪屋内
Cosy inside their igloo,
卢卡西和朋友们必须静静等待
Lukasi and his friends must now wait.
在捕食之前
Before they can hunt,
会出现一些奇特的现象
something extraordinary has to happen.
在海冰之下
Underneath the sea ice,
潮水逐渐退去
the tide is going out
一点一点地
and out.
这片浮冰居然下沉了12米
The floating ice drops a staggering 12 metres,
约40英尺
nearly 40 feet,
露出了海床  也希望
exposing the seabed, and, hopefully,
会带来他们迫切需要的食物
the bounty they're after.
卢卡西和朋友们试着
Lukasi and his friends try to get
尽快下到冰层之下
under the ice as quickly as possible.
在潮水回流之前
They have just half an hour
他们只有半小时
before the tide comes back in.
我们做的最胆战心惊的事...
就是走下冰层
他们脚下的世界毫不牢固
The world beneath their feet is unstable.
巨大的冰块缺乏海水的支撑
The giant blocks of ice are no longer supported by water
可能会随时崩塌
and could collapse at any moment.
地球上只有这个地方
This is the only place on Earth
潮水涨退的落差极大
where the tides are extreme enough
让人们有胆量在海冰层下探险
to allow people to dare venture under the sea ice.
在这个不久前还充斥着海水的冰窖里
And in a chamber that moments ago was underwater,
他们找到了所需要的东西
they find what they're looking for.
贻贝
Mussels.
他们所期盼的也仅此而已
All they could hope for.
现在他们争分夺秒  尽可能多地捡贻贝
Now they have just minutes to gather all they can carry.
潮水涨起时  无人能阻止
The returning tide is an unstoppable force.
我们都了解贻贝捕食者的故事
...关于那些无法及时返回地面的捕食者
如果你没法脱身
你就会死
当海水逐渐回流
As the sea steadily flows back,
会托起千斤重的冰块
it lifts the huge blocks of ice over their heads.
大水来了  快走吧
就在他们撤退时  冰块就在他们身边浮起
Even as they escape, the ice shifts around them.
大海要收回它的神秘花园了
The ocean reclaims its secret garden.
卢卡西只能在大潮期这几天里
Lukasi can only harvest mussels
去捡拾贻贝
for the few days of extreme tides.
这些贻贝真不错
贻贝是我们冬日食物的重要来源
在终日以鱼和肉为食的冬天
Mussels are a delicious way to break up a diet
用贻贝来换换口味让人觉得美滋滋的
that during winter has been mainly seal meat and fish.
但夏日将至
But summer is on the way,
万物将变
and everything is about to change.
到六月  阳光使气温回升至零度以上
By June, the sun finally pushes temperatures above zero.
冰海将融
The sea ice begins to melt.
待到浮冰融化之时
And as it breaks apart,
一年一度的夏季迁徙就开始了
it triggers an annual summer migration.
远离海岸整整一个冬季的动物们
Animals that have spent the winter far offshore
开始追随着融冰向海湾进发
follow the melting ice into the bays and fjords.
这是北极猎人们千载难逢的机会
For Arctic hunters, this creates a unique opportunity.
马穆拉・克里斯蒂安森
Mamarut Kristiansen,
以及他的兄弟米克莱和葛迪恩
and his brothers Mikele and Gedion,
是北格陵兰岛的因纽特人
are Thule Inuit from northern Greenland.
他们急着奔赴狩猎行程中
They're rushing to keep the most important appointment
最重要的约会
in their hunting calendar.
他们必须得准时
They must be punctual.
几周后  他们所踩覆的冰块
In just a few weeks, the sea ice
就会消失殆尽
they're travelling on will melt away.
他们的目标是北极最珍稀的食物
Their goal is the most precious food in the Arctic.
独角鲸
Narwhal.
这些传奇般的鲸也向海湾行进
These legendary whales are looking for a way into the bay.
这是一种神秘的生物
This is a mythic creature...
但却富含着北极最稀有的维生素
...but it is also a source of the rarest vitamin in the Arctic.
维生素C
Vitamin C.
在这片果蔬贫瘠的土地上
In a landscape with so few edible fruits or plants,
因纽特人别无选择
the Inuit don't have alternatives.
他们在那儿
它们不想靠近冰缘...
独角鲸难能一见
Spotting narwhal is hard enough.
即便科学家也很少见到它们
Even scientists who study them rarely see them.
但若米克莱想抓住一条
But if Mikele is going to catch one,
这些独角鲸得再游近些了
the narwhal will have to swim a great deal closer than this.
我看不见它们了...
它们会回来的
好几周后  三兄弟才再次看见了独角鲸
It could be weeks before the three brothers see narwhal again.
他们仍得保持警惕  还有很多准备要做
But they have to stay alert, and there's plenty to prepare.
这里的法律规定
In this region, the law states
猎人们只能采取传统方法
that hunters can only use traditional methods.
也就是得划着独木舟
This means travelling in kayaks,
一种因纽特人千年沿袭下来的船
a craft the Inuit invented thousands of years ago,
还要用Avatak[一种捕鱼工具]
and using the avatak,
一种用环斑海豹皮做成的浮标
a buoy made from the skin of a ring seal.
给我讲个睡前故事吧
别再睡过头了
也别老打呼噜
即便午夜时分  阳光依旧灿烂
Even though it's midnight, the sun still shines.
六月的太阳在天空盘旋
In June, the sun simply circles the sky,
从不落下
never dipping below the horizon.
我要睡觉了...
你会一直看着的吧
真舒服...
要保持始终有一人守卫  这很关键
It's vital that one of them stands guard at all times.
但葛迪恩不只要找寻独角鲸
But Gedion isn't just looking for narwhal.
他还要观察冰面
He's watching the ice.
冰层已经薄到快裂开来了
Already it's thinning and breaking apart.
一不小心
If they're not careful,
三兄弟很可能会发现
the brothers could find themselves
自己置身于漂浮的融冰之上
adrift on a melting piece of ice.
这些年来
这些冰块一直是我们心头之患...
他们融的太快了
我们想要靠近独角鲸...
变得更难了
但一旦真来了的话...
你得做好准备
马穆拉和葛迪恩知道绝不能慌张
Mamarut and Gedion know not to panic.
独角鲸相当的谨小慎微
Narwhal are extremely skittish,
所以他们小心翼翼地涉入水中
so the hunters enter the water with care.
哪怕一丁点错误
哪怕是划桨时动作大了一点
他们都会立刻察觉到
兄弟齐心
The three brothers work as a team.
他们仅以某只独角鲸为目标
They're after just one whale.
他们采用埋伏战略
It's an ambush.
独角鲸离米克莱只有50英尺远[15米]
The narwhal pass within 50 feet of Mikele
但他们仍按兵不动
but still all three hunters wait.
太早行动
If he strikes too soon,
只会满盘皆输
the whole pod will dive.
他瞄准了殿后的那条鲸
His eye is on the stragglers bringing up the rear.
尤其在这最后关头
Especially in the final approach,
米克莱必须静静地跟随着猎物
Mikele must be silent and directly behind his prey.
全家的温饱都肩负在他们身上
Their success will benefit the whole community.
一条独角鲸即使不能满足一家成月的需求
The single narwhal will feed their families for weeks,
也能管饱几个星期
if not months.
我们的祖先物尽其用
所有动物都有价值
而我们也继承了他们的衣钵
独角鲸最值钱的部位是它的皮
The most prized part of the narwhal is the skin.
他们称之为鲸脂
They call it muktuk.
这是他们最主要的维生素C来源
It's their primary source of vitamin C.
独角鲸中  维生素C的含量
Ounce for ounce, narwhal skin contains
几乎和橘子一样多
almost as much vitamin C as oranges.
味道不错
没有这些独角鲸  很难想象
Without narwhal,it's doubtful
因纽特人怎样在北极大陆上存活下来
the Inuit would have survived in this part of the Arctic.
时值六月  太阳赢得了胜利
It's now July, and the sun finally wins its battle.
冰面融化成广阔的海洋
The sea ice melts into open ocean.
要想找到食物  人们将目标转向大陆
To find food, man turns his attention to the land.
位于格陵兰岛的西奥拉帕卢克
Siorapaluk, Greenland,
是地球上最北的原始居留地
is the northernmost native settlement on Earth.
每年
Every year,
马恒咖・欧师马都有幸一睹
Maassannguaq Oshima is treated to a spectacle.
成千上万的海雀迁徙之景
Millions of little auks on migration.
它们来这里的悬崖繁衍后代
They come here to breed on the cliffs.
对捕食者来说
And for predators,
这里满天飞舞的食物让它们垂涎三尺
there's a mouth-watering supply of protein whizzing overhead.
问题是得够得着
If you can reach it.
千年前  马恒咖的祖先
Thousands of years ago, Maassannguaq's ancestors
用浮木与动物蹄筋制作出了捕鸟网
worked out how to make nets out of sinew and driftwood.
并发现了这处他正藏身与其中的捕猎之所
And they created the same hiding spots he uses today.
我们等这些海雀
等了一年了
他们是夏日的美味
天气好的话  马恒咖能捕到将近500只
On a good day, Maassannguaq can gather up to 500 birds.
但他却不急着吃
But he won't eat them now.
他要向他的动物伙伴学习
He'll take his cue from a fellow hunter.
北极狐经常把一些鸟埋起来
Arctic foxes often stuff a few birds underground,
这样没东西吃的时候
so that when times are lean,
他们就有备粮了
they'll have food to fall back on.
为了熬过寒冬  充分准备是很必要的
要想活下来  你需要储备好食物
这些鸟会被用来做成Kiviak[一种发酵食物]
The birds can be used to make kiviak,
一种为雨天而储备的食物
a dish that you save for a rainy day.
其烹饪方法有数千年的历史
The recipe is thousands of years old,
具体是这样做的
and it goes like this.
取一张海豹皮
Take one seal skin.
往里面塞尽可能多的海雀
Stuff as many little auks inside it as you can.
至少500只
At least 500.
把它缝起来
Sew it up.
确保排出所有空气
Make sure you press all the air out.
海豹的脂肪可以驱蝇
Seal fat repels flies,
所以缝合口尽量多涂抹点
so be generous when coating the seams.
最后盖上大石头  确保没有空气进入
And finally, use a big rock to make sure no more air gets in.
马恒咖的这份Kiviak得等上三个月
Maassannguaq's kiviak won't be ready for three months,
不过冰冻的大地是天然的冰箱
but the frozen ground is a natural refrigerator.
冬天来时
Come winter,
他和他的家人就有充足的食物了
he and his family will have a vital supply of food.
现在到了九月份
It's now September.
日照变短  气温骤降
Days are getting shorter and temperatures are plummeting.
那些在北极短暂的夏日里
The few plants that have managed to grow
长出来少数植物  变得蔫蔫一息
over the short Arctic summer are dying back.
这是挪威北部亚挪岛上
This is exactly what is happening on Arnoy island,
人们生活的真实写照
northern Norway.
三千只驯鹿在此吃了一个夏天的草
3,000 reindeer have been grazing here all summer.
但如今  它们得走了
But now they have to move,
因为它们冬天的食物来源  地衣
because their winter food source,lichen,
要到450千米远外才能找到
can only be found 450 kilometres away.
为了觅食  它们必须横渡
And to get to it, they'll have to cross this,
亚挪海峡
the Arnoy strait.
艾莉埃莱尼・斯里的职责
Elle-Helene Siri is in charge
就是带领这些驯鹿过河
of leading these reindeer across the water.
先带这么多吧...
她来自一个放养驯鹿的萨米人家庭
She belongs to a family of Sami reindeer herders.
迁徙之前
Before the migration begins,
艾莉把鹿分成小组
Elle helps split the deer into smaller groups
这样他们才能给驯鹿喂药
so they can give them vital medicine.
这项工作很危险
驯鹿是一种有着锋利茸角的野生动物
从艾莉出生那天起
On the day she was born,
她就负责照顾这一群驯鹿
Elle was given a portion of this herd.
如今20岁的她毕业于挪威驯鹿学院
Now aged 20, and a recent graduate of Norway's reindeer college,
她要确保这些驯鹿
it's up to her to make sure they all survive
在接下来的征途中存活下来
the perilous journey ahead.
让这些鹿乖乖地迁到冬季牧场
It will take nearly a month for these deer
要花近一个月的时间
to migrate to their winter pastures.
但今天是最困难的一天
But today is the toughest day of all,
因为鹿群要游到2.5千米外的对岸
because the deer have to swim 2.5 kilometres across the channel.
刺骨的北冰洋此时的水温刚过冰点
These chilly Arctic waters are only just above freezing.
即使对于成年驯鹿  这也是一次漫长的旅行
Even for adult reindeer this is a long swim.
对于今年才出生
But for this year's calves,
从未下过水的小仔们
which have never been in the water before,
这将是一场马拉松
it's a marathon.
在整场大迁徙中...
最危险的部分就是横渡海峡
很多地方都有可能出问题...
尤其是小鹿
加油  继续游
当年轻的幼崽游到一半时
As the young calves approach the halfway point,
已然疲惫不堪
exhaustion sets in.
对于艾莉而言  此时决不能掉以轻心
For Elle, it's a tense moment,
因为一旦有一头小鹿打道回府
because if one calf turns around and swims back,
其余的都可能紧随其后
the rest could follow.
在过去  共有150小鹿...
...因为害怕而回头
你必须时刻盯紧它们
一头小母鹿遇到了麻烦
A baby female is in trouble,
突然  她掉转了方向
and suddenly, she turns back.
艾莉必须马上阻止她
Elle must stop her
否则整场迁徙都可能前功尽弃
or the whole migration could derail.
来吧  继续游
她做到了
She's done it.
大迁徙一切正常
The migration remains on track.
经过了一个小时艰难的横渡之行
After an hour of hard swimming,
艾莉和她的驯鹿终于到达了对岸
Elle and her reindeer reach the mainland.
真高兴它们成功横渡了海峡
我也算卸下了肩头重担
我非常高兴
不久以后  艾莉的驯鹿就能吃到
It won't be long before Elle's deer will be grazing
它们在寒冬赖以为生的地衣了
on the lichen they need to get them through the winter.
不仅仅是动物
And it's not just animals
此时为了觅食而出动
looking for a meal at this time of year.
在格陵兰岛  马恒咖和他父亲
In Greenland, Maassannguaq and his father
也准备动用他们夏天储存的
are already breaking into the caches of little auks
食物海雀了
they stored up in the summer.
鸟儿现在已经发酵完毕
The birds have now fermented and have become
成了因纽特人的一道美食  Kiviak
the Inuit delicacy known as kiviak.
通过气味可以轻松分辨
It's easy to tell
你的Kiviak是否发酵好了
if your kiviak is ready by the aroma.
闻上去应该有些刺鼻
It should sting the nostrils.
这就是为什么最好在室外吃Kiviak
This is why it's polite always to serve kiviak outdoors.
它的味道
The flavour should resemble
就像重口味的戈贡佐拉奶酪
extremely intense Gorgonzola cheese.
一丁点都不能浪费  都是可以吃下去的
Nothing is wasted. Everything is edible.
装了新假牙后...
我又可以咬碎骨头了
格陵兰岛北部的
The Inuit of northern Greenland
因纽特人非常喜爱Kiviak
love kiviak so much
更是将它奉作生日和婚宴的首选
that it's the dish of choice for birthdays and weddings.
而它所富含的营养物质
And it's nutritious,
维生素以及矿物质
full of vitamins and minerals
可以支撑人们度过严冬
that will sustain people over the winter months ahead.
随着九月将尽  十月来临
As September gives way to October,
冬天又重新回到北极地带
winter returns to the Arctic.
海洋再次千里冰封
The ocean ices over once again.
最先结冰的地区中  就有哈得逊湾
One of the first places to freeze lies along Hudson's Bay
靠近马尼托巴省[加拿大]的丘吉尔港
near the town of Churchill, Manitoba.
每年  这里的一千多个居民
Every year, the 1,000 human residents
都不得不与
must share their town
世界上为数不多的经常会猎杀人类的
with one of the few predators on Earth
掠食动物共处一方
that actively hunts human beings.
从九月到十一月
From September to November,
将近300多头饥肠辘辘的北极熊
as many as 300 ravenous polar bears
会在回冰原猎食的路上
descend on Churchill
涌入丘吉尔市
on their way back to hunt on the sea ice.
鲍勃・温沙负责保护居民安全
Bob Windsor is in charge of protecting the residents.
他是"北极熊示警队"
He belongs to a special task force -
特别工作组的成员
the Polar Bear Alert team.
北极熊是地道的捕食性动物
Polar bears are pure predators,
它们以猎杀其他动物为生
so they kill other animals to eat.
这是它们的生存方式
That's how they survive.
也就是说  面对北极熊要非常谨慎
Knowing that, you have to give them a little more respect
因为你也很可能成为它的盘中之餐
because you could also be a potential meal for them.
这里是190[呼叫代码]
This is one nine zero.
通知大家
Just to let everybody know
目前正有一头熊向镇上靠近
that there's a bear coming towards town.
作为第一道防线
As a first line of defence,
鲍勃试图将这头熊吓回荒野
Bob tries to frighten the bear back into the wilderness.
但这样的遭遇战不会就此结束
But this skirmish isn't necessarily over.
由于急需食物充饥
Desperate for something to eat,
北极熊经常会在夜色的掩护下重返小城
bears often return in the cover of darkness,
对于鲍勃来说尤其糟糕
which is bad news for Bob,
因为今晚  相比平时
because tonight, more than any other night,
更加需要戒惧
fills him with dread.
万圣夜对我们来说可能是
Halloween is probably the busiest night
一年之中最忙的一个晚上了
of the yearthat we work,
因为这天晚上会有大量居民
just by the sheer number of people
会外出活动
out and about that evening.
所以  发生意外的可能性
So, the potential for something bad
是显而易见的
to happen is definitely there.
当"不给糖就捣乱"的孩子们走街串巷时
At the same time as the trick-or-treaters hit the streets,
人们聚集在皇家协会酒吧
people at the Royal Legion gather for
参加每周一次的肉类抽奖活动
their weekly meat raffle.
奖品是上等的加拿大牛肉
The prize for winning is prime Canadian beef.
下一位幸运者
Next ticket...
440号
number 440.
这样单独行动看起来有些不够小心
This may seem cavalier,
但是丘吉尔市的居民拒绝活在恐惧之中
but the residents of Churchill refuse to live in fear.
而且有北极熊示警队员的巡逻保护
And the protection of the polar bear patrol
他们也非常放心
makes them feel safe.
然而  在过去
However, in the past,
北极熊曾在主街上
bears have mauled and killed people
袭击并杀死了居民
right here on Main Street,
所以鲍勃再怎么警惕都不为过
and Bob is all too aware of the risks.
你总是祈祷
You always hope and pray
不要发生任何意外
that nothing bad is gonna happen.
保持警惕
Keep your eyes open,
注意周围一举一动  并时刻想着
be aware of your surroundings and always be thinking
附近可能就有一头熊
that there could be a bear nearby.
它们会四处走动  但你察觉不到
They'll move around. You won't hear them.
不给糖就捣乱
Hi! Trick or treat!
有时我们称它们为幽灵
We kind of refer to them sometimes as ghosts,
因为它就在你眼皮底下消失了
cos they'll just disappear on you.
又在另一处出现  然后呢  会去哪里
They'll be there, then, "Where did it go?"
这样想还挺惊悚的
A little spooky that way.
它们的速度出奇地快  动作敏捷
They're amazingly fast, amazingly agile,
而且悄无声息
and amazingly stealthful.
不给糖就捣乱
Trick or treat!
-你们好  怎么样  -玩"不给糖就捣乱"呢
- Hi, guys! How you doin'?  - Trick or treat.
在要糖吃
Trick or treat?
有北极熊出没吗
Have you seen any bears?
没有  今夜很太平
No, it's been good tonight.
早些时候是有一头出现在镇上
There was a bear in town earlier today.
但今晚一切平安无事
But there's been nothing tonight at all.
听到了吗  我们很安全
Did you hear that? We're safe.
祝你们玩得愉快
You have a good night tonight, OK?
要对北极熊保持警惕  好不好
Keep your eyes open for polar bears too, OK?
-谢谢  -再见
- Thank you, guys.  - Bye-bye!
-万圣节快乐  -回见  小灰熊
- Happy Halloween!  - See you, little bear!
万圣节快乐呦
Happy Halloweenie!
今晚  丘吉尔市的居民安然无恙
Tonight, the residents of Churchill are safe,
但他们并不知道刚好逃过一劫
but it was a closer call than many of them realised.
捕熊陷阱内的情况即可证明
Inside this bear trap is proof
要糖的人们并不是
trick-or-treaters weren't the only ones
昨晚唯一在街上晃悠的
on the streets last night.
被海豹肉诱捕进笼的这头熊
Lured into the cage by seal meat,
是头雄性北极熊  重达半吨
this male weighs over half a ton.
打了镇静剂后被运往
This bear is sedated and will be flown
60公里以外远离城镇的郊外
at least 60 kilometres outside of town.
在以往
In the past,
平均每年有75头入侵的北极熊
an average of 75 bears per year
被运出丘吉尔市
have been transported out of Churchill.
不过近年来
But in recent years,
这个数字已经减少了一半
the number of invading bears has halved
因为在北极的这片地区
because in this part of the Arctic,
北极熊数量正逐年下降
polar bears are in decline.
他们计算了镇静剂的用量
They have timed the sedative
这样着陆后不久  北极熊就会苏醒过来
so that it wears off soon after they land
这样做是为了保护它
This is done so that bears can protect themselves
不会受到同地区其他北极熊的伤害
from other bears in the area.
对温沙警官而言
For Officer Windsor,
这意味着在熊完全醒来前
it means working fast
要迅速完成任务
before this bear fully wakes up.
否则这样一头雄性北极熊的一巴掌
A single swipe from a male
也可能是致命的
this size could be fatal.
把它们放生的感觉很好
It's a great feeling cos here it is, you're letting them go.
你不禁会好奇它接下来会去哪里
You can't help but wonder where's it going to be going,
如何生活
how is it going to make out.
看到一头熊再爬起来
Very satisfying to see a bear
继续它的道路  这种感觉很满足
actually get up and go on its way.
希望它一切都好
Wish 'em well, hope for the best,
也希望不要再在镇上看到它
and hope to never seem 'em again in town.
随着海面迅速结冰
With the sea ice forming fast,
这头北极熊很快就能在
it won't be long before this polar bear
宽广的冰面上悠哉觅食了
can roam far and wide in search of food.
但对于北极周围居住的人类而言
But for people, moving around the Arctic
却更为危险了
is about to get a lot more treacherous,
因为太阳正渐渐离他们而去
because the sun is deserting them.
现在是十一月  格陵兰岛的伊卢利萨特
It's November in Ilulissat, Greenland,
太阳将不再从海平面上升起
and the sun no longer rises above the horizon.
接下来的54天  人们看不见日光
The residents won't see daylight for another 54 days.
他们努力做到和平时一样
They try to live their lives as normal.
依旧打渔捕猎
They still hunt and fish.
大人们去工作
Adults go to work.
孩子们去上学
Children go to school.
但这一切都笼罩在黑暗之中
But it's all under the cover of darkness.
当黑暗的日子绵延不止
As the dark days drag on,
每个人都渴望阳光的再次降临
everybody yearns for the sun to come back.
终于  在1月13日
Finally, on January 13th,
他们的愿望实现了
they get their wish.
所有人都出门庆贺
The entire community comes out to celebrate
迎接新年的第一缕阳光
the first sunrise of the new year.
生生不息的太阳
...照亮了黑夜中的灵魂
...普洒大地的阳光
每一次黎明的到来  都逐渐让北极变暖
With every new sunrise, the Arctic is warming up.
...驱散了内心的寒冷
而在未来的几年中  由于季节变迁
And the seasonal opportunities that have made life possible
人们赖以生存的自然条件也许会不复存在
may not be here in years to come.
但是北极圈的居民们生而顽强
However, the people of the Arctic are born survivors.
如果说有谁能够适应即将来临的变化
If there's anyone who can adapt to the changes on the horizon,
那便是他们
surely it's them.
人类星球
镜头背后的故事
对于北极小分队来说
For the Arctic team,
捕猎独角鲸的挑战不小
the narwhal hunt was always going to be a challenge.
捕猎通常在春天进行
The hunt happens in the spring,
但那时海面冰层最为脆弱危险
when the sea ice is at its most fragile and dangerous.
尽管知道有风险  但没有人能预计到
Even knowing the risks, no-one could have foreseen
在这变幻莫测的土地上
quite how much drama
他们会得到怎样戏剧性的际遇
they would face in this treacherous place.
格陵兰  卡纳克
北纬77°28’48” 西经69°21’36”
冰雪上的第一天
Day one on the ice,
经验丰富的摄制组和极地摄影师道格・艾伦
and the experienced crew, including polar cameraman Doug Allan,
都忙于将行装搬运到雪橇上
are busy loading the sleds.
这就是六个人在冰天雪地要度过两周
This is what you need to take six people onto the ice
道格・艾伦
摄影师
所需的全部行装
for a fortnight.
东西真挺多的  是吧
It's a hell of a lot of stuff, isn't it?
我们六人有共计约400公斤的行装
We've probably got about 400 kilos between six people.
西蒙・福瑞斯特
录音师
所以  要说我们是轻装上阵
So, to say we're travelling light is possibly
是有点夸张了
a little understatement!
每辆雪橇上坐一个人和一部分行装
With the kit and a person on board,
因此每辆的负重约在100公斤左右
each dogsled is having to carry about 100 kilos of freight,
这对于12条雪橇犬来说实在有些重
which is quite a lot, really, between 12 dogs.
但饲养它们就是为了派上这个用场
But this is what these dogs are bred for,
它们做起来也得心应手
and they're in their element.
他们动身穿越27公里的冰面
They set off across 27 kilometres
抵达无冰的海面
of sea ice to open water.
马穆拉  葛迪恩和米克莱三兄弟
Three brothers, Mamarut, Gedion and Mikele,
应邀带领着摄制组去捕独角鲸
lead the crew on their quest for narwhal.
仅仅几个小时以后
After only a couple of hours,
探险队就看到了第一个危险讯号
the expedition encounters their first sign of danger.
你可以清楚地看到这里的冰层在移动
You can quite distinctly see the movement here.
此处隆起是由无冰海域的海水涌进引起的
The swell's coming in from the open ocean
它使得冰层开始破裂
and it's breaking it up.
此处小裂痕
And this little crack here,
能容纳一指宽度
which you can put your finger down,
也许是15分钟前形成的  且还会扩大
maybe 15 minutes from now, it's going to be this wide.
再过半小时  它就会宽到跨都跨不过了
Half an hour, it will be too wide to cross.
必须得小心应对
You have to be careful.
这片冰层时时刻刻都在移动
This ice is on the move all the time.
因纽特猎人们认为冰层太不稳定
The Inuit hunters decide the ice is too unstable
探险被迫折返到安全的陆面上
and the expedition is forced back to the safety of land.
经历五个半小时
After five and a half hours of travelling,
我们已经穿过了海湾口
we've come all the way across the...the inlet.
但冰层仍不稳定
The ice edge is still unstable
因此我觉得我们得在这过夜
so I think we'll wait the night out here
明天看看情况如何再做决定
and then maybe have a look-see tomorrow.
次日早晨
The next morning,
他们小心地跨过冰缝走向雪橇
they pick their way across broken tidal ice to the sleds,
去查探情况如何
to check out the situation.
我很庆幸猎人们昨日做出了明智的决定
I'm pleased the hunters made the decision they did,
因为昨晚
as overnight,
冰架塌陷了近三四公里
we've lost three or four kilometres of the ice shelf,
而且那个方向的冰层仍在继续迅速消失
which is now disappearing rapidly in that direction.
随着我们进入峡湾
As we were coming into the fjord,
我们实际上又与来路交叉了
we actually crossed our tracks,
但来路已经融化成了海洋
and they disappeared into the water,
想起来实在是后怕
which was quite a sobering thought.
当他们真的到达冰层尽头时
When they do reach the edge,
他们简直不敢相信自己运气这么好
they can't believe their luck,
因为马穆拉很快就看到了一些独角鲸
as Mamarut quickly spots some narwhal.
我们在远处的冰层边缘看到了一些独角鲸
We've just seen some narwhal further along the ice edge,
大伙们都开始去准备独木舟了
so the guys are getting the kayaks ready
独角鲸一旦靠近
because if the narwhals come close,
他们就会试图捕捉
they might try to hunt them.
道格已经准备好捕捉那一刻了
Doug's ready to capture the action.
但正当葛迪恩要落下鱼叉时
But just when Gedion is in position to harpoon,
独角鲸下潜了
the narwhal dives.
他们等待着  期望鲸鱼再度浮出水面
They wait and hope for the whales to resurface.
现在是凌晨一点钟
It's now one o'clock in the morning.
我们已在此蹲点十二个小时了
We've been here for about 12 hours.
独角鲸已离去
The narwhal have gone
但猎人们坚信它们还会再回来的
but the hunters are still sure that they're going to come back,
我们依然在等待
and we're still waiting,
并且开始变得非常疲惫
and we're all getting very tired.
全日不休的阳光融化了表层的冰
24-hour daylight melts the ice from above,
海浪不停地在冰下鼓动着
and ocean swells stress the ice from beneath.
在这里扎营并不安全
It's not the safest place to camp,
但他们必须在冰层边缘等待独角鲸归来
but they must wait at the edge for the narwhals' return.
等待由以天计变成了以周计
The days start to run into weeks
摄制组不得不延长拍摄计划
and the crew have to extend their shoot.
我们在此已停留了三周之久
It's almost three weeks now that we've been on location
而这就是问题所在
and this...this is the problem
冰
ice.
这下面肯定有独角鲸
And somewhere under here are the narwhals.
这真叫人沮丧
It's really frustrating.
现在  天气也对他们不利了
Next, it's the weather that turns against them.
真是祸不单行啊  是吧
It's just one thing after another, isn't it?
我要告诉你我无聊到了什么程度
I'll tell you how bored I am.
什么程度
How bored are you?
我今早把我的帐篷移了位
I moved my tent this morning.
这是我这三天内做过最有意思的事情了
That was the most exciting thing I've done in three days.
我把它移动了六英尺
And I moved it six feet.
我有种成就感  终于感觉自己做了点事
It gave me a sense of satisfaction, cos I'd done something!
日子一天天过去  气温升高冰层变薄
As the days pass, the temperature rises and the ice thins,
风险也增加了
increasing the chance of something going wrong.
浪头越来越近...
我们也许得拔营回寨了
听到了吗  听到了吗  快听
Did you hear it? Did you hear it? Oh, listen, listen!
尼古拉斯・布朗
《人类星球》导演
冰层在破裂  我们脚下的冰层在破裂
It's cracking... It's cracking right underneath us right now.
因为有雪覆盖因此你们看不到
You can't see it cos there's snow on top of it.
就像有声音  "E啦"
There was like, "Crunch!"
这是捕鲸的最好时机  完美的光线
It's perfect narwhal conditions, perfect light,
完美的一切
perfect everything,
现在有涌浪
and what's happening, we've got swell.
涌浪能使任何地方的海冰破裂
The swell can fracture the sea ice literally anywhere.
这可不是好消息
That's not good news.
所以现在得快点离开  去安全地带
So, it's time to leave here and head to safer ground.
平时闲散的因纽特人加快了脚步
The normally laid-back Inuit up their pace,
摄制组也意识到了情况的严重性
and the crew realise the situation is serious.
走  快走
Go! Go!
必须要走了
Gotta go.
我们和卡纳克之间的路段...
...情况看起来不妙啊
有处裂缝宽达100码[90米]左右...
...它将在二三十分钟内彻底裂开
他们现在是真正的如履薄冰
They are all now cast adrift on an ice floe.
贝唐・埃文斯
《人类星球》研究组成员
我不知道我们到底要怎样才能离开这
I don't know how the hell we're going to get off this now!
现在情况紧急
They're facing an emergency
大家的关注点都变为  如何险中求生
and everyone's focus turns to survival.
别拍了  拜托
Stop this, please.
整个探险队正以惊人的速度撤离
The whole expedition is now floating away at an alarming rate.
全队共计有十三人  五十四只狗
There are 13 people, 54 dogs
六架雪橇的行装等待被转移至安全地带
and six sleds of kit to get to safety.
葛迪恩已爬进了他的小独木舟
Gedion has got into his canoe
正带着一根结实的引线  拼命划过冰缝
and is paddling furiously across the lead with a very fine trace wire,
看起来他们会用一根更粗的绳子
onto which, by the looks of it, they will put a much thicker rope,
在另一边来牵引雪橇过去
to physically haul from the other side the sleds across,
这办法很聪明  因为雪橇浮力不错
which is very clever, cos they float - amazing.
速度很重要
Speed is of the essence,
因为风把队伍吹得离陆地越来越远
as the wind blows the team further and further from land.
此处海水的温度会把人冻死
The sea temperature here can kill in minutes.
小心行驶不翻船是值得的
It pays not to rock the boat.
把重要的东西放上来
Get the important stuff on!
大家伙做得好
Well, the guys have done great.
很好  别拍打  他们知道该怎么办
Very impressed. No flap. They knew what to do.
经过四小时的运输
After four hours ferrying,
行装和摄制组都安全抵达对岸
the kit and crew reach the other side safely.
但不通水性的五十四只狗仍在对岸
But that still leaves 54 water-shy dogs.
而在对岸的那些  回家依然遥不可及
On the other side, they're still far from home
所立之冰层又正在破裂
and on ice that's breaking up around them.
这是在和时间赛跑
It's a race against time,
他们离安全的村庄仍有十公里以上的距离
as over 10km before they reach the safety of the village.
家乡近在眼前
Within sight of home,
一群缺乏经验的狗犯了个严重的错误
an inexperienced dog team makes a serious error.
一条被忽视的裂痕在离村庄数米处出现
An unseen crack has opened up just metres from the village.
裂缝再大一点 这满载物资的雪橇
Any wider and the fully laden sledge
就会直沉海底
would sink to the bottom,
且会一并拖下拉车的狗
dragging the dogs under.
有条狗被困在雪橇下了
There's a dog trapped under the sledge
但它却奇迹般地没有受伤
but, miraculously, even this one emerges unharmed.
道格和摄制组其他人看到这幕
Doug and the rest of crew spot the problem
便避开了那条道
and find a better route home.
在冰层重新变得足够安全
It was another week before the ice was safe enough
能拍摄捕鲸之前  他们又等了一周
for the crew to film the full narwhal hunt sequence.
在这里  生存与否全凭对环境的了解
This shoot, more than any other,
与其他拍摄过程相比  这次经历
highlights the importance of the complete trust
尤其证明了《人类星球》摄制组
between the Human Planet crew and the local Inuit,
与因纽特人间的互相信任  至关重要
in a place where knowing your environment is the key to survival.